Raise your hand if you've ever been asked the question
ارفع يدك إذا تم طرح هذا السؤال عليك في أي وقت مضى
"What do you want to be when you grow up?"
" ماذا تريد أن تصبح عندما تكبر؟ "
Now if you had to guess,
والآن فلنخمن،
how old would you say you were when you were first asked this question?
كم كان عمرك عندما طرح عليك هذا السؤال لأول مرة؟
You can just hold up fingers.
يمكنكم الإشارة إلى ذلك فقط بأصابعكم.
Three. Five. Three. Five. Five. OK.
ثلاثة. خمسة. ثلاثة. خمسة. خمسة. حسناً.
Now, raise your hand if the question
والآن ارفع يدك اذا تسبب لك هذا السؤال
"What do you want to be when you grow up?"
" ماذا تريد أن تصبح عندما تكبر؟ "
has ever caused you any anxiety.
بأي نوع من القلق.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Any anxiety at all.
أي قلق على الإطلاق.
I'm someone who's never been able to answer the question
أنا شخص لم أكن قادرًا على الإجابة عن هذا السؤال مطلقًا
"What do you want to be when you grow up?"
" ماذا تريد أن تصبح عندما تكبر؟ "
See, the problem wasn't that I didn't have any interests --
أترون؟ المشكلة لا تكمن في عدم امتلاكي أي اهتمامات --
it's that I had too many.
بل كوني لدي الكثير والكثير.
In high school, I liked English and math and art and I built websites
في المدرسة الثانوية أحببت الإنجليزية والرياضيات والفن وإنشاء مواقع الإنترنت
and I played guitar in a punk band called Frustrated Telephone Operator.
وقد لعبت الغيتار في فرقة مغفلة تدعى عامل الهاتف المحبط.
Maybe you've heard of us.
ربما سمعتم عنا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This continued after high school,
واستمر هذا بعد المدرسة الثانوية،
and at a certain point, I began to notice this pattern in myself
وفي لحظة معينة، بدأت ألاحظ هذا النمط بداخلي
where I would become interested in an area
عندما اهتم بشيء ما،
and I would dive in, become all-consumed,
فأنا أنغمس بكل جوارحي،
and I'd get to be pretty good at whatever it was,
حتى أصبح ماهرة في هذا الشيء مهما يكن،
and then I would hit this point where I'd start to get bored.
ثم أصل إلى مرحلة الضجر.
And usually I would try and persist anyway,
وفي العادة أحاول الاستمرار،
because I had already devoted so much time and energy
لأنني كرّست الكثير من الوقت والطاقة
and sometimes money into this field.
وفي بعض الأحيان المال في هذا المجال.
But eventually this sense of boredom,
لكن في النهاية هذا الشعور بالملل،
this feeling of, like, yeah, I got this, this isn't challenging anymore --
هذا الإحساس، مثلا، نعم، عرفت ذلك، لم يعد هذا تحديًا --
it would get to be too much.
سيتضخم.
And I would have to let it go.
وبالتالي أتركه.
But then I would become interested in something else,
ثم أهتم بشيء آخر،
something totally unrelated, and I would dive into that,
شيء مختلف تمامًا عما كنت مهتمة به،
and become all-consumed, and I'd be like, "Yes! I found my thing,"
وأنغمس في البحث بكل جوارحي، قائلة لنفسي "أخيرا لقد وجدت ضالتي"
and then I would hit this point again where I'd start to get bored.
ومن ثم أصل إلى تلك المرحلة من الضجر ثانية.
And eventually, I would let it go.
وفي النهاية أتركه.
But then I would discover something new and totally different,
ومن ثم اكتشف شيئا جديدًا كليًا،
and I would dive into that.
وأبدأ في البحث بكل جوارحي.
This pattern caused me a lot of anxiety,
تسبب لي نمط الحياة هذا في الكثير من القلق،
for two reasons.
لسببين.
The first was that I wasn't sure
السبب الأول لم أكن متأكدة
how I was going to turn any of this into a career.
من كيفية تحويل شغفي إلى مهنة.
I thought that I would eventually have to pick one thing,
فكرت في أنه في آخر المطاف لابد أن أختار شيئا واحدا فقط
deny all of my other passions,
وأنسى بقية اهتماماتي،
and just resign myself to being bored.
وأخضع للضجر الذي سيُصيبني.
The other reason it caused me so much anxiety
والسبب الثاني الذي تسبب لي بالكثير من القلق
was a little bit more personal.
كان شخصيا قليلًا.
I worried that there was something wrong with this,
لقد كنت قلقة من وجود خطب ما،
and something wrong with me for being unable to stick with anything.
خطب ما بي أنا، لعدم قدرتي على التمسك بشيء واحد فقط.
I worried that I was afraid of commitment,
كنت متخوفة من عدم قدرتي على الإلتزام،
or that I was scattered, or that I was self-sabotaging,
أو كنت مشتتة التفكير، أو مخربة لنفسي،
afraid of my own success.
متخوفة من نجاحي.
If you can relate to my story and to these feelings,
إن كنتم مررتم بقصة مشابهة وشعرتم بنفس الأحاسيس
I'd like you to ask yourself a question
أريدكم أن تسألوا أنفسكم سؤالا
that I wish I had asked myself back then.
والذي تمنيت لو سألته لنفسي من قبل.
Ask yourself where you learned to assign the meaning of wrong or abnormal
اسأل نفسك أين تعلمت تعريف معنى خاطئ وغير طبيعي
to doing many things.
للقيام بعدة أشياء.
I'll tell you where you learned it:
سوف أخبركم أين تعلمتم ذلك:
you learned it from the culture.
لقد تعلمتموه من الثقافة.
We are first asked the question "What do you want to be when you grow up?"
يتم سؤالنا في البدء " ماذا تريد أن تصبح عندما تكبر؟ "
when we're about five years old.
عند عمر الخامسة تقريبًا.
And the truth is that no one really cares what you say when you're that age.
وفي الحقيقة لا أحد يُعطي أهمية لما تقوله حينها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's considered an innocuous question,
يتم اعتباره كسؤال عديم الضرر،
posed to little kids to elicit cute replies,
يتم طرحه على الأطفال الصغار للحصول على ردود لطيفة،
like, "I want to be an astronaut," or "I want to be a ballerina,"
مثل "أريد أن أصبح رائد فضاء" أو "أريد أن أصبح راقصة باليه"،
or "I want to be a pirate."
أو" أريد أن أصبح قرصاناً".
Insert Halloween costume here.
وهنا إدراج ملابس الهالوين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But this question gets asked of us again and again as we get older
ولكن مع تقدمنا في السن يتم طرح هذا السؤال علينا مرارًا وتكرارًا
in various forms -- for instance, high school students might get asked
في أشكال مختلفة -- على سبيل المثال ربما يتم سؤال التلاميذ في
what major they're going to pick in college.
المدرسة الثانوية لاختيار تخصص لدراسته في الجامعة.
And at some point,
وفي وقت ما يتحول السؤال،
"What do you want to be when you grow up?"
" ماذا تريد أن تصبح عندما تكبر؟ "
goes from being the cute exercise it once was
من سؤال مرح
to the thing that keeps us up at night.
إلى ما يشغلنا ليلا.
Why?
لماذا؟
See, while this question inspires kids to dream about what they could be,
في حين أنا هذا السؤال يُلهم الأطفال للحلم بما يريدون أن يُصبحوا عليه،
it does not inspire them to dream about all that they could be.
إلا أنه لا يلهمهم للحلم بكل ما يمكن أن يُصبحوا عليه.
In fact, it does just the opposite,
ولكن على العكس،
because when someone asks you what you want to be,
عندما يسألك شخص عما تريد أن تُصبح عليه،
you can't reply with 20 different things,
لا تستطيع الإجابة بعشرين شيئًا مختلفًا،
though well-meaning adults will likely chuckle and be like,
بالرغم من أن البالغين سيبتسمون ويقولون،
"Oh, how cute, but you can't be a violin maker and a psychologist.
"أوه، كم هذا ظريف، ولكن لا يمكنك أن تكون عازف كمان وطبيب نفسي في نفس الوقت.
You have to choose."
يجب عليك أن تختار".
This is Dr. Bob Childs --
هذا هو الدكتور بوب تشايلدز--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
and he's a luthier and psychotherapist.
وهو صانع للأدوات الوترية ومعالج نفسي.
And this is Amy Ng, a magazine editor turned illustrator, entrepreneur,
وهذه آمي نج، محررة بمجلة تحولت إلى رسامة ورائدة أعمال،
teacher and creative director.
ومعلمة ومخرجة إبداعية.
But most kids don't hear about people like this.
ولكن أغلب الأطفال لا يسمعون عن أناس كهؤلاء.
All they hear
كل ما يسمعونه
is that they're going to have to choose.
هو أن عليهم الإختيار.
But it's more than that.
ولكن الأمر يتعدى ذلك.
The notion of the narrowly focused life
إن مفهوم التركيز على شيء واحد في الحياة
is highly romanticized in our culture.
مترسخ للغاية في ثقافتنا.
It's this idea of destiny or the one true calling,
هي فكرة القدر هذه أو النداء الوحيد الحقيقي.
the idea that we each have one great thing
فكرة أنه لكل واحد منا شيء عظيم واحد
we are meant to do during our time on this earth,
يمكنه القيام به على هذا الكون،
and you need to figure out what that thing is
ويجب أن تكتشف ماهو ذلك الشيء
and devote your life to it.
وأن تكرس حياتك من أجله.
But what if you're someone who isn't wired this way?
ولكن ماذا إن كنت شخصا لا تثيره هذه الطريقة؟
What if there are a lot of different subjects that you're curious about,
ماذا لو كانت تثير فضولك العديد من المواضيع المختلفة،
and many different things you want to do?
وتريد القيام بعدة أشياء؟
Well, there is no room for someone like you in this framework.
حسنا، لا يوجد مكان لأمثالك في هذا الإطار.
And so you might feel alone.
وهكذا قد تشعر بالوحدة.
You might feel like you don't have a purpose.
قد تشعر بأنه ليس لديك هدف.
And you might feel like there's something wrong with you.
كما قد تشعر بأن هناك خطب ما بك.
There's nothing wrong with you.
لا يوجد أي خطب ما بك.
What you are is a multipotentialite.
الحالة التي أنت فيها هي تعدد مقدراتك الكامنة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
A multipotentialite is someone with many interests and creative pursuits.
ذو القدرات الكامنة المتعددة هو شخص لديه العديد من الإهتمامات والهوايات المبدعة.
It's a mouthful to say.
إنها كلمة صعبة النطق.
It might help if you break it up into three parts:
يمكن أن تكون أسهل إذا قسمت الكلمة إلى ثلاثة أجزاء:
multi, potential, and ite.
متعدد والقدرات والكامنة.
You can also use one of the other terms that connote the same idea,
يمكنك استعمال أحد المصطلحات الأخرى التي تُشير إلى نفس المعنى،
such as polymath, the Renaissance person.
مثل واسع المعرفة وشخص في عصرالنهضة.
Actually, during the Renaissance period,
في الحقيقة، خلال عصر النهضة،
it was considered the ideal to be well-versed in multiple disciplines.
اعتبر من الأمثل أن تكون لك دراية جيدة في عدة تخصصات.
Barbara Sher refers to us as "scanners."
بربارا شير تشير إلينا بمصطلح "النواسخ الضوئية".
Use whichever term you like, or invent your own.
استعمل أي مصطلح تريد أوابتكر مصطلحك الخاص.
I have to say I find it sort of fitting that as a community,
يجب أن أقول أنني أجده نوع من التصنيف،
we cannot agree on a single identity.
كمجتمع لا نستطيع الإتفاق على هوية واحدة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's easy to see your multipotentiality
من السهل أن تعتبر تعدد قواك الكامنة
as a limitation or an affliction that you need to overcome.
كقيد أو محنة تحتاج إلى التغلب عليها.
But what I've learned through speaking with people
ولكن ما تعلمته من خلال حديثي مع الأشخاص
and writing about these ideas on my website,
وكتاباتي حول هذه الأفكار على موقعي الخاص بي على الإنترنت،
is that there are some tremendous strengths to being this way.
أنه يوجد قوى هائلة كونك ضمن هؤلاء.
Here are three
وهاهي الثلاث
multipotentialite super powers.
قوى العظمى لتعدد القوى الكامنة .
One: idea synthesis.
أولا: تركيب الفكرة.
That is, combining two or more fields
والتي الجمع بين مجالين أو أكثر
and creating something new at the intersection.
وخلق شيء جديد عند التقاطع.
Sha Hwang and Rachel Binx drew from their shared interests
رسم كل من شا هوانغ ورايتشل بينكس اهتماماتهم المشتركة في مجالات
in cartography, data visualization, travel, mathematics and design,
رسم الخرائط، وتصور البيانات، والسفر، والرياضيات، والتصميم،
when they founded Meshu.
عندما أوجدوا "ميشو".
Meshu is a company that creates custom geographically-inspired jewelry.
"ميشو" هي شركة تصنع مجوهرات مستوحاة من الجغرافيا حسب الطلب.
Sha and Rachel came up with this unique idea
أتى شا ورايتشل بهذه الفكرة الفريدة من نوعها
not despite, but because of their eclectic mix of skills and experiences.
ليس على الرغم من بل بسبب الخليط الإنتقائي لمهاراتهم وخبراتهم.
Innovation happens at the intersections.
يُولّد الإبداع عند التقاطع.
That's where the new ideas come from.
من هنا تولد الأفكار الجديدة.
And multipotentialites, with all of their backgrounds,
والأشخاص ذوي القوى الكامنة المتعددة، مع كل خلفياتهم،
are able to access a lot of these points of intersection.
يمكنهم الوصول إلى عديد النقاط المشتركة.
The second multipotentialite superpower
وتكمن ثاني قوة عظمى لتعدد القوى الكامنة في
is rapid learning.
التعلم السريع.
When multipotentialites become interested in something,
عندما يهتم الأشخاص ذوي القوى الكامنة المتعددة بشيء
we go hard.
فنحن نبذل قصارى جهدنا.
We observe everything we can get our hands on.
فنحن نتأمل كل شيء نضع أيدينا عليه.
We're also used to being beginners,
فقد اعتدنا كوننا مبتدئين،
because we've been beginners so many times in the past,
بسبب أننا كنا مبتدئين عدة مرات في الماضي،
and this means that we're less afraid of trying new things
فهذا يعني أننا أقل خوفًا من تجربة أشياء جديدة
and stepping out of our comfort zones.
ولا نهاب الخروج عن منطقة راحتنا.
What's more, many skills are transferable across disciplines,
ماذا أيضا، يمكن نقل المهارات بين مختلف التخصصات،
and we bring everything we've learned to every new area we pursue,
ونجلب معنا كل ما تعلمناه إلى كل مجال نسعى إليه،
so we're rarely starting from scratch.
إذن نادرًا ما نبدأ من الصفر.
Nora Dunn is a full-time traveler and freelance writer.
نورا دون هي مسافرة بدوام كامل وكاتبة حرة.
As a child concert pianist, she honed an incredible ability
كطفلة تعزف على البيانو في الحفلات اكتسبت قدرة كبيرة
to develop muscle memory.
لتطوير عضلات الذاكرة.
Now, she's the fastest typist she knows.
والآن هي أسرع من يعمل على لوحة الحروف.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Before becoming a writer, Nora was a financial planner.
قبل أن تصبح كاتبة، كانت نورا مخططة مالية.
She had to learn the finer mechanics of sales
حيث كان ينبغي عليها أن تتعلم آليات البيع
when she was starting her practice,
عندما بدأت الممارسة،
and this skill now helps her write compelling pitches to editors.
ولقد ساعدتها هذه المهارة الآن على الإتيان بكتابات أخاذة للمحررين
It is rarely a waste of time to pursue something you're drawn to,
نادرا ما تكون مضيعة للوقت متابعة شيء كان يجذب انتباهك
even if you end up quitting.
حتى وإن انتهى بك المطاف للإعتزال.
You might apply that knowledge in a different field entirely,
فلربما ستوظف تلك المعرفة في مجال آخر مختلف تماما،
in a way that you couldn't have anticipated.
بطريقة لم تكن تتوقعها أبدًا.
The third multipotentialite superpower
وتكمن ثالث قوة عظمى لتعدد القوى الكامنة في
is adaptability;
القدرة على التكيف:
that is, the ability to morph into whatever you need to be
هذه هي، القدرة على التحول إلى كل ما تحتاج أن تكون عليه
in a given situation.
في وضعية ما.
Abe Cajudo is sometimes a video director, sometimes a web designer,
أبي كاجودو هو في بعض الأحيان مخرج أفلام وأحيانا أخرى مصمم مواقع إنترنت،
sometimes a Kickstarter consultant, sometimes a teacher,
وأحيانًا مستشار مشاريع بادئة وأحيانا معلم،
and sometimes, apparently, James Bond.
وأحيانا على ما يبدو جايمس بوند.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He's valuable because he does good work.
وهو ذو قيمة، بسبب قيامه بعمله على أحسن وجه.
He's even more valuable because he can take on various roles,
وأكثر من ذلك، فهو يستطيع إتقان عدة أدوار،
depending on his clients' needs.
حسب احتياجات زبونه.
Fast Company magazine identified adaptability
حددت مجلة "فاست كمبني" القدرة على التكيف
as the single most important skill to develop in order to thrive
كأهم مهارة للتطور بهدف الإزدهار
in the 21st century.
في القرن 21.
The economic world is changing so quickly and unpredictably
العالم الإقتصادي يتغير سريعًا وهو تغير غير متوقع
that it is the individuals and organizations that can pivot
لذلك فإن الأشخاص والمؤسسات القادرة على التغيير بهدف
in order to meet the needs of the market that are really going to thrive.
الإستجابة لحاجيات السوق هي التي ستزدهر.
Idea synthesis, rapid learning and adaptability:
تكوين الفكرة والتعلم السريع والقدرة على التكيف:
three skills that multipotentialites are very adept at,
ثلاث مهارات يبرع فيها الأشخاص ذوي القدرات الكامنة المتعددة،
and three skills that they might lose if pressured to narrow their focus.
وثلاث مهارات يمكن أن يخسروها في حالة التعرض لضغوط للتضييق على اهتماماتهم.
As a society, we have a vested interest in encouraging multipotentialites
كمجتمع، لدينا اهتمام بتشجيع الأشخاص ذوي القدرات الكامنة المتعددة
to be themselves.
ليكونوا أنفسهم.
We have a lot of complex, multidimensional problems in the world right now,
لدينا الكثير من المشاكل المعقدة ومتعددة الجوانب في العالم في الوقت الراهن،
and we need creative, out-of-the-box thinkers to tackle them.
ونحن بحاجة إلى مبدعين ومفكرين خارج الصندوق لمعالجة هذه المشاكل.
Now, let's say that you are, in your heart, a specialist.
والآن، فلنقل، في قرارة نفسك، أنت أخصّائي.
You came out of the womb knowing you wanted to be a pediatric neurosurgeon.
خرجت من رحم أمك وأنت تعرف بأنك تريد أن تصبح أخصائي جراحة أعصاب أطفال.
Don't worry -- there's nothing wrong with you, either.
لا تقلق -- لا يوجد بك أي خطب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In fact, some of the best teams are comprised of a specialist
في الواقع، أفضل الفرق تتكون
and multipotentialite paired together.
من مختصين وأشخاص ذوي قدرات كامنة متعددة.
The specialist can dive in deep and implement ideas,
يمكن للمختصين الغوص في الأعماق وتنفيذ الأفكار،
while the multipotentialite brings a breadth of knowledge to the project.
بينما يجلب ذوي القدرات الكامنة المتعددة اتساع المعرفة للمشروع.
It's a beautiful partnership.
إنها شراكة رائعة.
But we should all be designing lives and careers
ولكن ينبغي علينا جميعا تصميم حياة ومهن
that are aligned with how we're wired.
تتناسب مع ما يُثيرنا.
And sadly, multipotentialites are largely being encouraged
ولكن للأسف يتم تشجيع ذوي القدرات الكامنة المتعددة
simply to be more like their specialist peers.
ليكونوا مثل أقرانهم من المختصين.
So with that said,
إذن مما قلته،
if there is one thing you take away from this talk,
إذا كان هناك شيء يجب الخروج به من هذا الحديث،
I hope that it is this:
آمل أنه الآتي:
embrace your inner wiring, whatever that may be.
اتبع حدسك الداخلي مهما يكن.
If you're a specialist at heart,
إذا ما كنت أخصائي قلب،
then by all means, specialize.
إذن بكل الوسائل تخصّص.
That is where you'll do your best work.
هذا هو المجال الذي ستبرع فيه.
But to the multipotentialites in the room,
ولكن إلى كل ذوي القدرات الكامنة المتعددة في القاعة،
including those of you who may have just realized
بما في ذلك أولائك الذين أدركوا
in the last 12 minutes that you are one --
خلال 12 دقيقة الأخيرة أنهم ينتمون إليهم --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
to you I say:
أقول لكم:
embrace your many passions.
تقبل بكل سرور شغفك متعدد المجالات.
Follow your curiosity down those rabbit holes.
اتبع فضولك.
Explore your intersections.
اكتشف التقاطعات الخاصة بك.
Embracing our inner wiring leads to a happier, more authentic life.
اتباع حدسنا الداخلي سيقودنا إلى حياة أكثر سعادة وصدق.
And perhaps more importantly --
وربما الأهم من ذلك --
multipotentialites, the world needs us.
العالم في حاجة إلى ذوي القدرات الكامنة المتعددة أمثالنا.
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)